<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Deep-Learning on Hugo Veríssimo</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/deep-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Deep-Learning on Hugo Veríssimo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/deep-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sentiment Analysis of Financial Phrases</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/finphrasebank/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/finphrasebank/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project focused on sentiment analysis of financial phrases, based on the FinPhraseBank dataset, which contains sentences extracted from financial reports and news articles. The goal was to develop a model capable of classifying the sentiment of these phrases as positive, negative, or neutral, thus contributing to a better understanding of the emotional impact of financial information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The subset with 75% annotator agreement was used to ensure higher reliability of the labels. Of this dataset, 80% was used for training and 20% for testing, ensuring accurate performance evaluation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CPI Anomaly Detector</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/cpianomalies/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/cpianomalies/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project aims to detect anomalies in the Consumer Price Index (CPI), a key indicator used to measure inflation and the cost of living. The motivation is to identify unexpected and significant changes in consumer prices to support the analysis of economic dynamics and strategic decision-making.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Public data from over 200 countries was used to develop an adaptive, real-time (streaming) model capable of automatically detecting anomalies. The main model is based on Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) networks, with a focus on economic time series.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Counting Photovoltaic and Solar Panels from Aerial Images</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/solarpanel-dlcounter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/solarpanel-dlcounter/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project aims to count photovoltaic and solar panels from aerial images using Deep Learning and Computer Vision techniques. It was developed as part of the Zindi Lacuna competition, which provided images of panels in Madagascar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The work involved data cleaning and preprocessing, including correction of various polygons.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="display: flex; align-items: center; gap: 20px;">
 &lt;div style="flex: 1;">
 &lt;p>Creation of hybrid models combining ResNet, EfficientNet, and DenseNet to extract image features, with an attention head to aggregate features extracted from image metadata, for subsequent regression of the number of each panel type.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>