<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Computer-Vision on Hugo Veríssimo</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/computer-vision/</link><description>Recent content in Computer-Vision on Hugo Veríssimo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/computer-vision/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Smart Workbench</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/smartworkbench/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/smartworkbench/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of the Master&amp;rsquo;s Degree in Data Science at the University of Aveiro, in the Seminar course, our class created a fictitious startup called Smart Workbench, aiming to develop a system based on unstructured data (cameras) and structured data (timings and logs) to automate and optimize a production line.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The goal was to maximize line efficiency by reducing wait times and increasing productivity through data analysis and the use of machine learning and deep learning algorithms, helping predict failures, optimize processes, and reduce operators&amp;rsquo; cognitive load.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Counting Photovoltaic and Solar Panels from Aerial Images</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/solarpanel-dlcounter/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/solarpanel-dlcounter/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project aims to count photovoltaic and solar panels from aerial images using Deep Learning and Computer Vision techniques. It was developed as part of the Zindi Lacuna competition, which provided images of panels in Madagascar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The work involved data cleaning and preprocessing, including correction of various polygons.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="display: flex; align-items: center; gap: 20px;">
 &lt;div style="flex: 1;">
 &lt;p>Creation of hybrid models combining ResNet, EfficientNet, and DenseNet to extract image features, with an attention head to aggregate features extracted from image metadata, for subsequent regression of the number of each panel type.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>