<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Spark on Hugo Veríssimo</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/spark/</link><description>Recent content in Spark on Hugo Veríssimo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/spark/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>LSH Recommender System</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lshrecommender/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lshrecommender/</guid><description>&lt;p>Creation and benchmarking of a rating prediction algorithm based on LSH (Locality Sensitive Hashing) for large volumes of data from the MovieLens dataset. The goal is to predict a user&amp;rsquo;s rating for a specific movie, using advanced hashing techniques to optimize the search for similarities between users and movies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The algorithm was implemented in a high-performance computing environment, executed via SSH with distributed jobs on Apache Spark. This approach enables analysis and recommendation on large-scale datasets, ranging from 100 thousand to 25 million ratings, demonstrating the scalability and efficiency of the system in big data contexts.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lupa Digital</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</guid><description>&lt;p>Lupa Digital is a project developed within the scope of the Arquivo.pt Awards 2025 competition, focused on intelligent metajournalism. Using artificial intelligence tools, the project analyzes thousands of journalistic articles since the dawn of the digital era to discover patterns, trends, and relevant insights on any topic. The goal is to transform large volumes of journalistic information into useful and accessible knowledge, contributing to the strengthening of media literacy and a more critical understanding of the information ecosystem.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>