<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nlp on Hugo Veríssimo</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/nlp/</link><description>Recent content in Nlp on Hugo Veríssimo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/nlp/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Sentiment Analysis of Financial Phrases</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/finphrasebank/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/finphrasebank/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project focused on sentiment analysis of financial phrases, based on the FinPhraseBank dataset, which contains sentences extracted from financial reports and news articles. The goal was to develop a model capable of classifying the sentiment of these phrases as positive, negative, or neutral, thus contributing to a better understanding of the emotional impact of financial information.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The subset with 75% annotator agreement was used to ensure higher reliability of the labels. Of this dataset, 80% was used for training and 20% for testing, ensuring accurate performance evaluation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lupa Digital</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</guid><description>&lt;p>Lupa Digital is a project developed within the scope of the Arquivo.pt Awards 2025 competition, focused on intelligent metajournalism. Using artificial intelligence tools, the project analyzes thousands of journalistic articles since the dawn of the digital era to discover patterns, trends, and relevant insights on any topic. The goal is to transform large volumes of journalistic information into useful and accessible knowledge, contributing to the strengthening of media literacy and a more critical understanding of the information ecosystem.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Media Coverage Analysis of PSI-20 Companies</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/infomosaic/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/infomosaic/</guid><description>&lt;p>The main goal of this project is to analyze media coverage of companies listed on the PSI-20 index. Using data analysis, machine learning, and visualization techniques, the project aims to extract relevant insights about public perception and sentiment surrounding these companies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The specific objectives and features of the project include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Sentiment Analysis&lt;br>
Assess the sentiment in news articles and media coverage to determine whether keywords associated with PSI-20 companies have a positive or negative impact on public perception.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>