<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Machine-Learning on Hugo Veríssimo</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/machine-learning/</link><description>Recent content in Machine-Learning on Hugo Veríssimo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/tags/machine-learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Lupa Digital</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/lupadigital25/</guid><description>&lt;p>Lupa Digital is a project developed within the scope of the Arquivo.pt Awards 2025 competition, focused on intelligent metajournalism. Using artificial intelligence tools, the project analyzes thousands of journalistic articles since the dawn of the digital era to discover patterns, trends, and relevant insights on any topic. The goal is to transform large volumes of journalistic information into useful and accessible knowledge, contributing to the strengthening of media literacy and a more critical understanding of the information ecosystem.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantitative Research @ JPMorgan Chase &amp; Co.</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/jpm-quantitative-models/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/jpm-quantitative-models/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project uses quantitative research methods, machine learning, and data analysis to solve challenges in the financial and energy sectors. The analysis focuses on developing pricing models for natural gas contracts, estimating loan default probabilities, and forecasting losses for banks. Techniques such as K-means clustering, machine learning methods, and time series decomposition were employed to provide actionable insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Project highlights:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Development of a prototype pricing model for natural gas contracts, based on estimated prices for buying/selling on specific dates, gas injection/withdrawal rates in storage, and associated costs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Recommender Systems</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/mldriven-collabfilter/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/mldriven-collabfilter/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project involved exploratory analysis of a movie ratings dataset, with the goal of predicting the rating a user would give to a movie based on ratings from other users.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Two manually built linear regression models were used to predict ratings: one based solely on users and their ratings, and another incorporating movie metadata as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The FunkSVD model was also implemented.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The methodology included selecting the best hyperparameters through cross-validation, as well as choosing the final model based on RMSE and MAE metrics. Additionally, Precision@k, Recall@k, F1@k, and MRR@k metrics were used to evaluate the recommendation models&amp;rsquo; performance.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Media Coverage Analysis of PSI-20 Companies</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/infomosaic/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/infomosaic/</guid><description>&lt;p>The main goal of this project is to analyze media coverage of companies listed on the PSI-20 index. Using data analysis, machine learning, and visualization techniques, the project aims to extract relevant insights about public perception and sentiment surrounding these companies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The specific objectives and features of the project include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Sentiment Analysis&lt;br>
Assess the sentiment in news articles and media coverage to determine whether keywords associated with PSI-20 companies have a positive or negative impact on public perception.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fatigue Classification in Competitive Swimmers</title><link>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/swimml-fatiguemonitor/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://hugoverissimo21.github.io/projects/swimml-fatiguemonitor/</guid><description>&lt;p>This project focuses on applying Machine Learning to estimate fatigue levels in swimmers, with the goal of preventing overuse injuries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Data was collected from a local swimming team, covering multiple athletes. Data preprocessing was conducted to ensure quality, integrity, and suitability for machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Feature engineering extracted relevant variables from raw data, notably using EWMA (Exponentially Weighted Moving Average).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Models such as Support Vector Machine (SVM), logistic regression, and decision trees were used to classify data into three fatigue levels.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>